Student Association; Records ua804
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Student Association Records
1921-2013
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua804
6.5 cubic ft.
The Student Association Records contains records documenting the proceedings of the UAlbany Student Association from its inception in 1921 to 1989. This collection contains records that relate to the changing duties, functions, and governmental structure of the Student Association.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this record group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the Student Association.
Administrative History
The current Student Association was formed in 1921. Interest in forming a student government dates from 1914. At that time, President Milne rejected a student petition to form a student government commenting, "There is no place in this institution for the association and activities contemplated in this petition". President A.R. Brubacher(1915-1939) took a more favorable attitude toward student government. In response to a 1915 student petition, he instructed Professor Risley to form a committee to study the possibility of creating a student government. There appears to have been an attempt at forming a rudimentary student organization in January, 1916. As a result of Risley's study, Myskania was formed in 1917. Myskania, referred to in their 1917 constitution as the student council, was an honorary body consisting entirely of seniors who were to represent "the opinion and to improve the department of the student body." Myskania, in turn, created the Student Association in 1921. The general business of running student funded activities such as the yearbook and the student newspaper appears to have been the concern of the Student Assembly. The new Student Association appears to have carried on the responsibilities of the Student Assembly. (For a history of Myskania, see the Myskania finding aid.)
The Student Association's original purpose as stated in its 1921 constitution, was "the management of all matters of student interest not academic in nature." The Student Association controlled the legislative, financial and executive powers of the government, while Myskania acted as a single judicial branch and as guardian of school traditions. According to the 1921 constitution, the executive duties of the S.A. fell on the executive board made up of the president, the vice president, the secretary and the treasurer. The Executive Board's duty was to carry out the provisions of the Assembly and act as a court of appeals. By 1928, a new constitution for the Student Association changed the executive branch. Instead of the Executive Board, the executive branch was run by Student Council, different from the original student council (Myskania), which was made up of the president, the vice president, the secretary, and the presidents of the four classes. The new Student Council had broader duties than the Executive Board including: arranging the program for Student Association meetings, providing for the publication of the student directory, charter all boards, committees and associations by securing support from the Student Association through the budget and executing all legislation passed by the Student Association.
In the 1930's and 40's Student Association assemblies dealt with contemporary issues such as the presidential campaigns, the New Deal, and World War II. In 1949 the Student Association was involved in a project called CARE, an organization to help the children of the war. From the end of the 1960's the Student Association has placed increasing emphasis on student rights and equal opportunity. Minorities began to organize themselves and form groups including the Women's Liberation Front, Black Students Alliance and Lesbians for Freedom and the Student Association gave formal recognition to these new organizations. The trend continues to this day. At the same time the Student Association supported new programs such as the Equal Opportunity Program (EOP), developed in 1973.
While continuing to sponsor equal opportunity programs for all races and creeds, the Student Association has also, in more recent years, turned its attention to the environment (NYPIRG was recognized on campus in 1982), as well as supported such academic initiatives as the Frosh Reading Program. Long term issues include opposition to ROTC, during the 1960's and 70's for its support for the United States Government's Vietnam War policy, in the 1980's because ROTC discriminated against gay and lesbian candidates; reproductive rights and the establishment of a Birth Control Center on campus. The prominent development of the 1970's through 1990's was the Student Association s new power in academic affairs--one prominent example of that was their accessing the competence of teaching faculty. The results of their surveys were distributed in the ACT and SCATE Booklets.
Scope and Contents
The Student Association record, consist of meeting minutes, subject files, student publications, booklets, bills and committee files.
Includes minutes of the Student Association and Central Council, 1921-49, 1969-89; Cenral Council bills and resolutions, 1966-89; subject files, 1940-44, 1959-88, consisting of a budget, constitutions, ACT (teaching assessment) proposals, announcements and newsletters; and committee records, 1941-88.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Student Association and Central Council Minutes, 1921-29, 1932-41, 1943-49, 1966-68, 1970-74, 1975-77, 1978-86, 1987-1989
Series 2 - Central Council Bills, 1965/66-1988/89
Series 3 - Subject Files, 1940-44, 1958-88
Series 4 - Committee Files, 1949-75
Series 5 - Assessment of Courses and Teachers (ACT and SCATE booklets), 1974-76, 1987, 1991
All series are arranged alphabetically with the exception of Series 1 and Series 2, which are arranged chronologically.
Athletics and Sports; Student government--United States; Albany (N.Y.); Newsletters; Administrative records; Membership; Minutes; Programs (documents); Financial Records; Correspondences; Web Archives; UAlbany Student Groups; University at Albany Foundation
- Meeting Minutes, 1968-2004; 1; 3 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The earliest minutes date from the formation of the Student Association in 1921. They document the Student Association's interest in establishing and maintaining school traditions (1920's and 30's), the Student Association 's concern with academic issues such as the establishment of the honor system. These documents give an overview of the management of the organization, and document the Student Association structural change.
  - Minutes-Central Council, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minutes-Central Council, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Item 3)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1986/1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
    - Central Council Minutes, 1996-10-02
    - Central Council Minutes, 1996-10-09
    - Central Council Minutes, 1996-10-16
  - Meeting Agendas, 1996 May-1997 April (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Central Council - Minutes, 1998 March (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Attendance, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1998 October 7 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1998 October 14 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1998 October 21 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1998 October 28 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1998 December 9 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1999 February 24 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1999 April 14 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1999 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1999 May 5 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1999 May 12 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1999 October 6 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1999 October 20 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1999 October 27 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 1999 November 4 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1999 November 11 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Minutes, 1999 November 18 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Minutes, 1999 December 1 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Minutes, 1999 December 8 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Minutes, 2000 January 26 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Minutes, 2000 February 15 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Minutes, 2000 February 23 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Minutes, 2000 March 1 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Minutes, 2000 March 15 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Minutes, 2000 March 29 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Minutes, 2000 April 5 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Minutes, 2000 April 12 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Minutes, 2000 May 3 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Minutes, 2000 May 16-2000 May 17 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Agenda and Bills, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Agenda and Bills, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Attendence, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Agendas, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Legislation, 1965-2013; 2; 2 cubic ft.
  The Central Council Bills are complete for the period 1965-66 to 1988-89. This series contains bills passed by the Central Council which is the legislative body of the student government. The bill relate to appropriations, budgets, recognition of student organizations, resolutions relating to local, state, national and international issues, student government reorganizations. The bills dating from 1978-79 to 1988-89 are bound and indexed from 1978-79 through 1985-86
  - Bills - Central Council #7, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bills - Central Council #47-49, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bills - Central Council #45, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bills - Central Council # 14,25,32,97,125,143, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bills - Central Council #49,54,58-64,68,81,82,84, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bills - Central Council #2,3,4,5,6,7,8, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bills and Resolutions, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bills - Central Council [requires disbinding before digitization], 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bills - Central Council, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bills - Central Council, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bills - Central Council, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Bills - Central Council, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Bills - Central Council, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Bills - Central Council, 2010-2011 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Bills - Central Council, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Bills - Central Council, 2012-2013 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1968-1991; 3; 0.5 cubic ft.
  The Student Association gained the permission of the Administration to publish surveys of courses and teachers which are available to the students so that they could make more informed decisions in choosing their courses. The collection is incomplete, and while the faculty evaluations from the 1970's appear to be comprehensive, those from the 1980's and 1990's only publish ratings of a few courses where the faculty has given permission to publish.
  - Student Evaluations of Courses and Teachers, 1968 Fall (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Student Evaluations of Courses and Teachers, 1969 Spring (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1974 Spring (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1974 Spring (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1974 Spring (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1974 Fall (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1974 Fall (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1974 Fall (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers (ACT) Blank Questionaires, 1974-1975; 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1975 Spring (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1975 Spring (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1975 Spring (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1976 April (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1976 April (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Assessment of Courses and Teachers, 1979 Spring (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Student Course and Evaluation, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Student Course and Teacher Evaluation, 1991 April (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Subject Files, 1940-1988; 4; 1.17 cubic ft.
  This series contains constitutions, budgets, ACT teaching assessment proposals, announcements and newsletters, Moving-up Day programs, and government reorganization papers. In some cases there is extensive information on proposals such as the ACT's and the Ebenezer Howard Project, 1970-71, an attempt to involve students in the problems of urban poverty. The subjects range from local to state wide concerns including other SUNY schools.
  - Academic Affairs Commission Report to Central Council, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Academic Affairs Commission, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Accountants Report: Financial Statements and Supplementary, 1967 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Air Force ROTC "Cross-Town" Agreement, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Announcements - Assorted, 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Athletic Advisory Board- Budget, Rules, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Athletic Advisory Board SA Bills and Minutes, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ballots, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Big 4 Committee - Recommendations, 1949-1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bits and Pieces-A.S.A. Newsletter, 1970; 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Budgets, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Budgets-Requests, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Budgets, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Budgets, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Budgets, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Budgets-Summary, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Budgets, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Budget Committee Minutes, 1979 March 26; 1979 April 03 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Central Council-Parking Strike, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Central Council-Student Tax Police, Nomination Form, Correspondence and Flyers, ca. 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Central Council-Supreme Court Application, ca. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Committee Reports and Recommendations, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Committee Reports and Recommendations, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Committee to Draft Campus Alchol Policy-Recommendation, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Committee on University Government Governance-SUNY Binghamton, Buffalo, Albany, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Composition Services - SA - Styles and Sizes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Consolidated laws and Regulations of Student Association, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Consolidated laws and Regulations of Student Association, 1976 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Constitution (Tenative) of the State College Student Association, 1945 May 15 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Constitution-Student Association "Board", ca. 1962 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Constitution, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Constitutional Revision Committee, 1965; 1969 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Constitution, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Constitution, Undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence-Assorted, 1951; 1959; 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Directories, 1970-1977 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Ebenezer Howard Project, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Election Commission - Ballots, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Elections - Flyers, 1972-1978; 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Faculty Student Association Budget, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Financial Policies (SA), Undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Financial Resolutions, 1943-1949 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Financial Statements, 1974 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Flyers and Brochures-Assorted, ca. 1970-1986 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Forms (blank) - Assorted, ca. 1965-1977 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Form Letters to Faculty Members, 1952; 1970; 1972; 1976; 1985 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Form Letters to Students and Their Parents, ca. 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Government Reorganization Committee, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Government Reorganization Committee Correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Government Revision Workshop, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - "Groups"-Directory of Student and Other Groups Recognized by The Student Association of SUNYA, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Informer-Issues #1 and #2, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Living Area Affairs Commission-Rationale for Women's Hours, 1967 March 15 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Memorandum - Assorted, 1968-1975 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Moving-Up Date Programs and Recommendations, ca. 1940-1960 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - NYCT Leadership Conference, 1954 May 23 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Off-Campus Student Co-Op, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Operating Expenses: Central Council, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Press Release-Concerning The Bill, Restoration of Carver Community Health Center Funding, 1973 October 5 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Procedures for Organizational Recognition, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Schedule for Letter Writing Campaign, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Student Affairs Council Minutes, 1975 February 5; 1974 March 6 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Student Association Handbook-SUNY Plattsburgh, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Student Evaluation of Courses Teachers-Blank Questionnaires and Instructions, ca. 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Student Government Conference-Information, Correspondence and Memoranda, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Student Government Reorganization Workshop, 1964 November 21 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Web Archives, 2006 August 30-2016 September 17; 7; 552 captures
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Web crawling is managed through the Internet Archive's Archive-It service. This page includes links to both the university's collection and the Internet Archive's public collection.
  Surface-level crawling of www.albany.edu is performed daily which should includes most top-level webpages. Separate targeted crawls of every albany.edu subdomain are performed monthly to attempt to gather all content. This includes: www.albany.edu, www.rna.albany.edu, www.ctg.albany.edu, www.ualbanysports.com, www.albany.edu/rockefeller, www.albany.edu/cela, www.albany.edu/asrc, m.albany.edu, library.albany.edu, events.albany.edu, cstar.cestm.albany.edu, csda.albany.edu, and alumni.albany.edu
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Web Archives
  - www.albany.edu/studentassociation/ - Internet Archive collection, 2006 August 30-2016 September 17 (Web-archive 2)